<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second summons to the city of Abel, 2 Sam. 20 to deliver up Sheba, the son of Bichri, that man of Belial : by way of metaphor, alluding to the Quakers and Geo. Whitehead and may serve for a reply to their answer to my printed sheet, stiled The Quakers Yearly Meeting impeached, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21466</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12683022</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12683022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65698</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65698)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 681:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second summons to the city of Abel, 2 Sam. 20 to deliver up Sheba, the son of Bichri, that man of Belial : by way of metaphor, alluding to the Quakers and Geo. Whitehead and may serve for a reply to their answer to my printed sheet, stiled The Quakers Yearly Meeting impeached, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by John Gwillam ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Francis Bugg, Senior.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:65698:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65698:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Second Summons to the City <hi>Abel, 2</hi> Sam. <hi>20.</hi> To deliver up <hi>Sheba,</hi> the Son of <hi>Bichri,</hi> that Man of <hi>Belial;</hi> by way of Metaphor, Alluding to the Quakers and <hi>Geo. Whitehead.</hi> And may ſerve for a Reply to their Anſwer to my Printed Sheet, ſtiled, <hi>The Quakers Yearly Meeting Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Geo. Whitehead,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have peruſed your Printed Sheet, as I have Reaſon to Judge, although 'tis Signed by five of your Undergraduates; <hi>being either aſhamed to appear your ſelf (as well you may) or elſe</hi> fearing that if your Name were to it, People would ſlight it, <hi>as not worth Reading,</hi> being the Fruit of an Old Contentious Make-bate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>That</hi> Wickliff, Suinderly, &amp;c. <hi>Teſtified againſt the Popiſh Clergy, and Tithes,</hi> &amp;c. By which you ſeem to make no difference between a Popiſh and Proteſtant Clergy, for which the Church of <hi>England</hi> will not thank you. But <hi>George,</hi> why do you thus fight with your own ſhadow, and thus trifle beſides the buſineſs? I did not Impeach the <hi>Quakers</hi> for not paying Tithes, though that be Criminal enough; but your <hi>Yearly Meeting,</hi> for <hi>Impoſing the non-payment of Tithes</hi> upon your People, and that too as a grand Oppreſſion, and Antichriſtian Yoke. And I ſay again, for you to Meet Annually, by way of Convocation, to make and promulgate ſuch Antimagiſtratical Laws, not only againſt, but contrary to the Laws of the Land; Is both againſt the King's Prerogative, the Rights of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and Property of the Subject; yea, and of dangerous Conſequence. And I ſay again, that by theſe your Cannon Laws you do actually Abſolve the King's Subjects <hi>(if the Quakers may be ſo called)</hi> from their Active Obedience to the Laws of the Land, which requires them to pay Tithes, Church-Wardens Rates, <hi>take Lawful Oaths,</hi> carry Guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſay you, theſe are but Epiſtles, and conſequently no contrived Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: But <hi>G. W.</hi> this will not do; it's true, you call them Epiſtles, but you ſend them down to your Monthly and Quarterly Meetings as Laws: And as <hi>Magna-Charta</hi> was <hi>formerly</hi> wont to be read in the Churches once, <hi>or oftner,</hi> every year, ſo do you Order your Epiſtles to be Recorded and Read in your Quarterly Meetings (which is more than ever you did the Scripture.) <hi>See your Epiſtle, ſtiled, Renewed Advice to the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales, &amp;c. And at the Concluſion you end thus: <hi>Record this Epiſtle in your Quarterly Book, and ſometimes read it for Remembrance and Notice.</hi> Thus 'tis plain that your Epiſtles
<pb facs="tcp:65698:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65698:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65698:3"/>
are Laws to your People, and as plain, that as the Power and Influence of your Yearly Meeting prevails, ſo muſt that of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> vail; ſince what is made Lawful at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> at your Yearly Meeting is made unlawful; yea, a Grand Oppreſſion, an Antichriſtian Yoke: And as ſuch you charge <hi>and Command</hi> your People not to pay Tithes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in my former Sheet more at large.</p>
            <p>And this Conſideration, together with your Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me for Printing without Licenſe<note n="*" place="margin">As your Indictment ſets forth, for I took a Copy of it, which poſſibly you may ſee hereafter, <hi>with ſome Obſervations upon it.</hi>
               </note>, although it be your own frequent Practice, put me upon delivering a Printed Sheet to the Parliament, ſtiled, <hi>Something in Anſwer to the Allegations of the Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dec.</hi> 1693.</p>
            <p>To which Sheet <hi>G. W.</hi> replyed and propoſed, ſaying, <hi>viz. I</hi> G. W. <hi>freely offer, and am willing to make it appear before <hi>any</hi> ſix, ten, or twelve competent Witneſſes, who are moderate Men of Senſe and common Reaſon, That</hi> Fr. Bugg <hi>has groſly abuſed and perverted Truth, and wronged the People called Quakers, both in Charge, Citation, and Obſervation,</hi> &amp;c. Now in Anſwer to this ſeeming fair offer, I came up to <hi>London</hi> the <hi>February</hi> following, and then proffered to meet <hi>G. W.</hi> and to leave Matter of Fact to the deciſion of four Men, choſen by each of us, out of Epiſcopalians, Presbyterians, Independants, or Baptiſts; or out of any one of thoſe four Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Societies. But this <hi>G. W.</hi> refuſed; but I held him to his word <hi>any,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed my Acceptation of his Propoſal, <hi>May</hi> 1695. but he ſtill refuſed to ſtand to his word: Then I <hi>Impeached</hi> their Yearly Meeting. And now in this their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>G. W.</hi> complains, ſaying, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>But now ſee how knowingly unfair</hi> Fr. Bugg <hi>is, after his railing againſt</hi> G. W. <hi>and the Quakers Books; as none ſo bad, none ſo groſs, none ſo blaſphemous, but</hi> G. W. <hi>the Quakers</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>will undertake to Vindicate them, who for theſe Forty Years and upwards hath been like</hi> Iſhmael, <hi>his Hand againſt Epiſco— Preſ— Indep. and Baptiſts, and theirs againſt him. Such then are</hi> Fr. Bugg's <hi>diſintereſted Perſons, whoſe hand is againſt</hi> G. W. <hi>(as he confeſſeth) And yet would have him leave Matters of Fact in Controverſie to their Judgment and Deciſion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I grant that Epiſcopalians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are great Enemies to the Errors of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and that ſome of all thoſe Societies have wrote againſt them, and that <hi>G. W</hi>'s. hand, like <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s hath been againſt them all. But this <hi>G. W.</hi> knew as well as I, before he made the proffer; his proffer was voluntary, <hi>and uncompelled</hi> to meet me before <hi>any</hi> eight, ten, or twelve moderate Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what to do? Why, to make it appear that <hi>Fr. Bugg had wronged the Quakers in Charge, Citation, and Obſervation.</hi> Now this is Matter of Fact; what, cannot he find four moderate Men in thoſe four Chriſtian Societies, that will do him that Juſtice, to Judge aright, whether <hi>Fr. Bugg</hi> cited the right Book, quoted the ſame Page, obſerving from thence the true ſenſe of the matter? Truly his pretence to a Charitable Diſtinction, in the <hi>Qua. Vind. p.</hi> 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. between the more moderate and the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> amounts to very little, if he dare not truſt their Judgment to decide whether <hi>Fr. Bugg</hi> rightly cited their Books, truly quoted their Pages, and from thence fairly obſerved the Senſe thereof, or no: But ſtill ſuppoſe they be ſuch Partial Wretches, as that eight or ten cannot be found amongſt them all; who is to be charged with unfairneſs? 'Tis not <hi>Fr. Bugg;</hi> he only takes <hi>G. W.</hi> at his word, [and holds him to it.] See <hi>Quaker. Withering,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 2. to 12. where this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65698:3"/>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But poſſibly ſome may ſay, You deal too ſeverely with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> not only by expoſing their Principles, but you render them Perjured, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Pilloring, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant ſome may blame me, yea, and good Men too; who do not ſee ſo clearly into their deceitful Practices as I do, and through much Experience have done. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> was a good Man, who was accounted the Light of that Age, yet he blamed <hi>Luther, Hiſt. of the Reformation,</hi> &amp;c. p. 42. <hi>Luther</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently admoniſhed the World in many things, I wiſh he had done it more civilly, he would have had more favourers and defenders, and have reaped for Chriſt a more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Harveſt,</hi> &amp;c. Thus you ſee that Zealous <hi>Luther</hi> was blamed by Worthy <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus:</hi> And if ſuch a Man as <hi>Luther</hi> was thus blamed, why ſhould I think it ſtrange? As to the Pillory, the occaſion of it was their falſifying their Word in the caſe of Evidence between <hi>G. W.</hi> and me: For they long before that, by their Books ſtiled, <hi>The Caſe of the People called Quakers, in relation to Oaths,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 26. And in another Book, ſtiled, <hi>A Treatiſe of Oaths,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 3. They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>A willingneſs to ſuffer, as in the Caſe of Perjury, in caſe they brake and falſified their Word,</hi> &amp;c. As at large recited in <hi>New Rome Arraigned,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Epiſt. to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans,</hi> &amp;c. And though I erected a Mock-Pillory, to ſhew them, what in reality they did deſerve, yet it had this Service, that it manifeſted their Perſecuting Spirit, and what they would be at, had they Power put into their hands. O! how did they fly to the Powers of the Earth (which they formerly blamed others for) crying out to Secretary <hi>Trenchard</hi> for help againſt <hi>Fr. Bugg!</hi> Yea, they Indicted<note n="*" place="margin">If they do deny it, I have a Copy out of the Court, with <hi>G. W</hi>'s. Name and the reſt: And their Indictment is in the moſt aggravatious terms that ever I ſaw.</note> me at the <hi>Old Bailey, London,</hi> when I was abſent Sixty Miles, and knew nothing of it. O! how did they ſollicite the Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of State againſt me! And did not <hi>W. Crouch</hi> give Five Pounds, and Promiſe a larger Sum, if he could have had their Revengeful Proſecution of me taken effect; and my Book, <hi>New Rome, &amp;c.</hi> (which they had got ſeized) to be burnt. With many other ſigns of their Perſecuting Spirit, which, had they Power, they would manifeſt more and more, as they did in <hi>Penſilvania</hi> to <hi>G. Keith</hi> and his Friends, where they both Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Impriſoned them, and took away <hi>R. B</hi>'s. Goods for Conſcience-ſake: Yea, ſo Inhumane were they, that when they Committed <hi>W. Bradford</hi> and <hi>John M'comb,</hi> one of their Wives was newly brought to Bed, and lay very weak <hi>in a High Fever,</hi> and ſeveral thought ſhe would not live; and <hi>though he requeſted them to let him go home,</hi> yet they would not grant him leave to ſee her. Oh, mercileſs Magiſtrates! I my ſelf, when a Quaker, was Priſoner at once more than three Years, yet <hi>during that time</hi> I had leave divers times to <hi>go home</hi> to viſit my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, which I find I muſt not expect if ever I be Priſoner under the Quakers, who being Magiſtrates in <hi>Penſilvania;</hi> can both Fine, Impriſon, and take away Goods, and fight with Carnal Weapons; both which, <hi>viz.</hi> Perſecutioh for Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, and Fighting with Carnal Weapons, they have pretended to be againſt. But now I ſee 'tis but till they get Power, and become Magiſtrates themſelves. And truly, if as <hi>T. C.</hi> hath modeſtly computed, there be but 100000 Quakers in <hi>England,</hi> and 1000 of them Preachers, and 1000 Meetings, and <hi>W. Pen</hi> Influence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65698:4"/>
(as he obſerves) but 80000 of them to Fighting and Perſecution, I know not what a little time may bring forth. For as <hi>T. C.</hi> well obſerves, <hi>They are but ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Seed now, but the full Crop may not appear in this Age;</hi> which puts me in mind of their former Declaration, Printed 1659. Signed by <hi>W. Crouch</hi> and four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen more, ſaying, <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>We have choſen the Son of God to be our King, and he hath choſen <hi>us</hi> to be his People: And he might Command Thouſands, and Ten Thouſands of his Servants at this day, to fight in his Cauſe, and give them Victory over all their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and turn his hand upon their Perſecutors. But yet his Kingdom is not of this World — Neither can we <hi>yet</hi> believe that he will make uſe of us in that way: — But for the <hi>preſent</hi> we are given up to bear and ſuffer all things for his Names-ſake.</hi> From whence it's plain, that in 1659. they ſaid, <hi>Neither can we</hi> yet <hi>believe:</hi> But by their Practice in <hi>Penſilvania</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1692. they believe they may now Fight and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute too. That in 1659. the Quakers ſaid, <hi>But for the <hi>preſent</hi> we are given up to bear and ſuffer all things for his Names-ſake:</hi> But by their Practice in <hi>Penſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania</hi> 1692. they ſay, they will not be affronted by any body: They will Fight with Guns and Swords, and Perſecute (ſuch as tell them they go from their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) with Fines and Impriſonment. Come, <hi>G. W.</hi> what is become of your Interpretation of the word <hi>as yet?</hi> What, is it <hi>tamen?</hi> I hope you ſee it to be <hi>Adhuc;</hi> as yet in exception to the time to come. I know you are good at <hi>Inuendo's,</hi> and at directing the Intention (Jeſuit like.) See his Book, ſtiled, <hi>The Light and Life of Chriſt within,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 58. <hi>Solomon Eccles</hi> (one of their Falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which propheſied that <hi>John Story</hi> ſhould dye within a Year, who lived three or four Years after) who ſaid, <hi>The Blood which was forced out of Chriſt's Body, when he was dead, was no more than the Blood of another Saint:</hi> Which Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy <hi>G. W.</hi> excuſes, ſaying, <hi>No more than the Blood of another Saint, his intent was, as to the Papiſts,</hi> &amp;c. Which Blaſphemy <hi>G. K.</hi> in his Book, ſtiled, <hi>A true Copy of a Paper,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 17. to 31. hath effectually diſcovered. And <hi>G. W.</hi> is ſo good at Directing the Intention, that he knows what all his Friends mean; for in his <hi>Counterf. Conv. &amp;c.</hi> p. 72. he ſays, <hi>I may ſee cauſe otherwiſe to word the matter, and yet our <hi>Intentions</hi> be the ſame:</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> of which is, though <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> deny Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> to be Chriſt, and make him but <hi>a Vail, a Garment,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>G.W.</hi> confeſs him to be the Chriſt, yet they mean all one thing, only a Garment. And (the Light) <hi>that was therein crucified is the Chriſt.</hi> And what was his Perſon to them more than another Perſon? Oh, but ſays his Young Pupil <hi>Pennington, The Diſcoverer Diſcovered,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>The Author of this Doctrine being nameleſs, I ſuppoſe he has forgot who it was: And truly I cannot blame him for forgetting what I believe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>had never any other Foundation but meer Imagination,</hi> &amp;c. Surely if his Infallible Spirit, with which they pretend to be endued, ſo as thereby to be furniſhed with Diſcerning and Judgment on all occaſions, (<hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 58.) could not tell him, yet <hi>G. W.</hi> might, for 'tis in <hi>The Chriſtian Doctrine and Society,</hi> by <hi>G. W. p.</hi> 5. and <hi>W. Baily</hi>'s <hi>Works, p.</hi> 300. 307. Come, <hi>G. W.</hi> ſince the Quakers are attained to that Perfection, as that they hold Courts of Judicature in the Name of the Honourable <hi>William Penn;</hi> And that you have Judges, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, Bailiffs, Conſtables, Goalors and Souldiers, Guns and Swords in <hi>Penſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> tell me the Intention of your great Apoſtle <hi>G. Fox,</hi> in his <hi>News coming up,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65698:4"/>
               <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>Sing, all ye Saints, and rejoyce, clap your hands, and be glad, for the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah will Reign</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> When we get Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours over <hi>Penſilvania</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c.</note>, <hi>and the Government ſhall be taken from you pretended Rulers, Judges and Juſtices, Lawyers and Conſtables; all this <hi>Tree</hi> muſt be <hi>Cut</hi> down,</hi> &amp;c. But I cannot enlarge at preſent on this Subject; but the more you ſtrive to cover and cloak your Errors, the more do you give occaſion to have them manifeſted; which puts me in mind of a Fable, recited by <hi>Luther, Malum irritatione auctum,</hi> A Sore groweth worſe by chaſing. And truly ſince our Scuffle firſt began about Womens Meetings, the Sect of the <hi>Foxonian Quakers</hi> (like the Man in the Fable) appears not only Lame, but Scabby, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the more they give occaſion, the more I rub and chafe this Corrupt Sore, until it will ſtink all the Nation over. If they again complain, that I put frightful Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them, let them withal remember, 'tis a Web of their own Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall ſhew what <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> the Founder of Quakeriſm, ſays of himſelf; next, what his Brethren, by way of Confirmation, ſay of him; and next, what the Quakers they ſay of the National Miniſtry, of the Scriptures, Sacraments, and of their own Writings, briefly and in Order.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt, of <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s Aſſuming Divine Attributes to himſelf.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>News coming up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <q>Written from the Mouth of the Lord, from one who is naked, and ſtands naked before the Lord, cloathed with Righteouſneſs, whoſe Name is not known in the World; Riſen up out of the North, which was propheſied of<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quere,</hi> by which Prophet?</note>, but now it is fulfilled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Several Petitions Anſwered,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 60. <q>My Name is covered from the World, and the World knows not me, nor my Name,</q> 
                  <hi>A Battledoor,</hi> &amp;c. Introd. <q>All Languages are to me no more than duſt, who was before Languages were, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> (Alike to <hi>James Parnel,</hi> in his Book, <hi>The Watcher,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <q>But to the end of all Diſputes and Arguments I am come, for before they was, <hi>I am.</hi> I have Power to bind and to looſe whom I pleaſe, from him whom the World calls <hi>George Fox,</hi> who is the <hi>Son of God.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>G. F. W. O. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Examination and Tryal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <q>The Thundering Voice anſwered [me <hi>Geo. Fox</hi>] <hi>I have glorified thee, and will glorifie thee again.</hi> And I was ſo filled full of Glory, that my Head and Ears was filled full of it.</q> 
                  <hi>A Journal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 31. 60. 67. <q>
                     <hi>I was in the Paradice of God;</hi> and that it was Chriſt the Eternal Power of God, that ſpake in me at that time unto them:— And that was the Word of the Lord, and of Chriſt through me to him: So that it was a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing unto them, when it was told them, the Man in Leathern Breeches is come.</q> See alſo <hi>p.</hi> 45. And for his pretended Miracles wrought in his own Name only, <hi>p.</hi> 371. 374. <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <q>And he that hath the ſame Spirit that raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt, is <hi>equal</hi> with God,</q> which Spirit <hi>G. Fox</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have. <hi>The Great Myſt. &amp;c. p.</hi> 894. <q>The Quakers have a Spirit given to them beyond all the fore-fathers (which we [ſaid <hi>G. F.</hi>] do Witneſs), ſince the days of the Apoſtles in the Apoſtacy. And they can diſcern who are Saints,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65698:5"/>
who are Devils, and who are Apoſtates, without ſpeaking ever a word.</q> 
                  <hi>The Great Myſtery, &amp;c. pag.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Reader, I have given you a few Inſtances of Blaſphemy, which hang and depend one upon another, as a Chain linked together. And the next ſhall be what his Preachers ſaid of him, by way of Corroboration. But firſt, hear what <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, in order to convince the World that <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> owned Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth;</hi> which indeed and in truth is no more nor leſs than he, <hi>G. F.</hi> ſaid of himſelf: A notable Proof, well may he be afraid, or aſhamed, or both, to meet me before moderate Men of ſenſe. Well, hear <hi>G. W.</hi> for once; <hi>A Juſt Enquiry,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 23. <q>And <hi>G. F.</hi> is more fully cleared from theſe Adverſaries Reproach in this matter by his own Innocent Teſtimony.</q> 
                  <hi>Great Myſt. p.</hi> 254. <q>That by Chriſt the Light, all things were made and created, and that he was glorified with the Father before the World began, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Well done, <hi>George.</hi> But now let us ſee if he do not ſay thus much of himſelf; and if ſo, what Paint haſt thou in ſtore next? <hi>The Teachers of the World unvailed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 27. <q>I am the Light of the World, him by whom the World was made: And doth enlighten every Man that cometh into the World<note n="*" place="margin">Meaning the Light in him.</note>
                  </q> Again, <hi>The Examination and Tryal at</hi> Lancaſter <hi>Aſſizes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <q>And before I came at the Bar, I was moved to Pray, and the Thundering Voice anſwered, <hi>I have glorified thee, and will glorifie thee again.</hi> I marvel that <hi>Whitehead</hi> ſhould have the Face to appear in Print with no better Proof that <hi>Fox</hi> owned Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth.</hi>
                  </q> Surely he may well be aſhamed to appear before any Men of ſenſe, to Juſtifie theſe his Abominations. And ſo much briefly for what <hi>Fox</hi> ſays of himſelf, and what <hi>Whitehead</hi> brings to excuſe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Quakers Adoring <hi>Geo. Fox, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>Fifth Part of the Chriſtian Quaker diſting. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 77. <q>
                     <hi>That</hi> G. Fox <hi>is bleſſed with Honour above many Brethren, and that Thouſands will ſtand by him in a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Record, That his Life Reigns, and is ſpotleſs, Innocent, and ſtill retains his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity;</hi> whoſe <hi>Eternal Honour,</hi> and Bleſſed Renown ſhall remain; yea, his Preſence, and the dropping of his tender words in the Lord's love was my Soul's Nouriſhment.</q> 
                  <hi>The Quakers Challenge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <q>Stand up, <hi>Muggleton</hi>— who calleſt thy Book, A Looking-Glaſs for <hi>Geo. Fox, whoſe Name thou art not worthy to take into thy mouth;</hi> who is a Prophet indeed, <hi>and hath been Faithful in the Lord's buſineſs from the beginning.</hi> It was ſaid of Chriſt, that he was in the World, and the World knew him not<note n="*" place="margin">Here <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>Sol. Eccles</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; <hi>G. F.</hi> ſaid, The world neither knew him, nor his Name; mark what Idolatry &amp; Blaſphemy is here.</note>. <hi>So</hi> it may be ſaid of <hi>this</hi> true Prophet, whom <hi>John</hi> ſaid he was not. But thou ſhalt feel this Prophet [<hi>i. e. G. F.</hi>] one day as heavy as a Mill-ſtone upon thee; And although the World knows him not, yet he is known, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſiah Cole</hi>'s Letter, wrote from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 21 of the twelfth Month, 1658. to <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> and vindicated by <hi>William Penn,</hi> in their Book <hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 44. <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>Dear <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> who art the Father of many Nations, whoſe Life hath reached through us thy Children, even to the Iſles afar off, to the begetting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65698:5"/>
many again to a lively hope, for which Generations to come ſhall call thee Bleſſed; whoſe <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>Habitation</hi> is in the Power of the Higheſt, in which thou <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Governs</hi> in <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> And <hi>thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> is <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> in Peace, and the <hi>Increaſe thereof</hi> is <hi>without end.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Audland</hi>'s Letter out of the Well of <hi>England,</hi> (which was Printed before <hi>G. F.</hi> dyed) taken out of the Original (which we have) an Abſtract thereof is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>Dear and Precious One, in whom my Life is bound up, my Strength in thee ſtand; by thy Breathings I am nouriſhed, by thee my Strength is renewed, Life and Strength came from thee, Holy ONE: Daily do I find thy Preſence with me, which doth exceedingly preſerve me, for I cannot Reign but in thy Preſence and Power. Pray for me, that I may ſtand in thy dread for evermore. I am thine, begotten and nouriſhed by thee, and in thy Power am I preſerved. Glory unto thee, Holy One, for ever.</q> See this Blaſphemous Letter more at large in <hi>The Diſcovery of the Accurſed Thing,</hi> by <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I remember when I charged the Quakers in my Sheet to the Parliament, <hi>Dec.</hi> 1693. <hi>p.</hi> 4. with their Contempt of the Publick Miniſtry, out of their Book, <hi>A Brief Diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. calling them (as falſe Miniſters) Witches, Devils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Geo. Whitehead,</hi> in <hi>The Quak. Vind. p.</hi> 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. denies that he knew the Book; and yet I find in his <hi>Juſt Enquiry,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 13. Printed ten Months before that, he could Anſwer it, tell the Title, Date, and number of Subſcribers, namely, five; ſaying, <hi>But ſtay, <hi>ſoft a little,</hi> were theſe Characters given in general, or to all other Miniſters that are not of us? <hi>No ſure.</hi>
                  </hi> In their <hi>Vindication,</hi> &amp;c. delivered to the Parliament, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. though he denyed to know the Book, yet he then could ſay, <hi>Yet his charging us with Contempt of the Publick Miniſtry, is too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and harſh; we Charitably diſtinguiſh between the more moderate ſort and the rigged Perſecutors,</hi> &amp;c. Well, let us ſee whether <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> be ſincere: He cries <hi>ſoft a little</hi> in one Book, and pretends Charitably to diſtinguiſh in the other Book: So that a ſtranger would think him very fair, at leaſt tolerable. But to prove him deceitful, and that they give thoſe Contemptuous Language to all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, nor Quakers, I ſhall make appear, for the Title over the Names is, <hi>Of the Falſe Miniſters.</hi> And therefore the way to find out <hi>G. W.</hi> is to Examine, Firſt, who they account Falſe Miniſters; and, Secondly, what Names they are pleaſed to beſtow upon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt, Who the Quakers Account Falſe Miniſters.</head>
               <p n="1">1. G. Fox <hi>his Primmer,</hi> p. 84. <q>
                     <hi>Scholar.</hi> Who have been the Miniſters and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors of the People, that they are erred ſo from Scripture-Example? Let me have ſome Marks and Signs, by which I may know the Deceivers and Falſe Prophets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> gives his Scholar Ten Inſtances againſt the Clergy, one is this, namely, <q>They are ſuch as ſprinkle Infants, and tell People, it is an Ordinance of Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Primmer.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <q>
                     <hi>Schol.</hi> How may I know when Chriſt is truly Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched? <hi>Anſw.</hi> They that are Falſe <hi>(Miniſters)</hi> Preach Chriſt without, and bid People believe in him as he is in Heaven above; but they that are Chriſt's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Preach Chriſt within.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:65698:6"/>3. <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 7. <q>All that do ſtudy to raiſe a living thing out of a dead, to raiſe the Spirit out of the Letter, are Conjurers: And the Lord is againſt all ſuch, and who are of God are againſt all ſuch.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Quakers Challenge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <q>Come, Proteſtants, Presbyterians, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants, and Baptiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Quakers deny you all,</q> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 3. <q>The Quakers are in the Truth, and none but they.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The Guide Miſtaken,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>W. Penn,</hi> p. 18. <q>And whileſt the Idle, Gorman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> run away with above 1500000 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> a Year, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being God's Miniſters; and that no ſort of People have been ſo Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally through Ages the bane of Soul and Body of the Univerſe, as that abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Tribe, for whom the Theatre of God's moſt Dreadful Vengeance is reſerved to Act their <hi>Eternal</hi> Tragedy upon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>An Antidote,</hi> by <hi>Thomas Ellwood,</hi> p. 78. <q>Truth allows of no Payment of Tithes at all under the New Covenant: They who Pay Tithes, uphold a Legal Ceremony abrogated by Chriſt, and thereby deny Chriſt to be come in the Fleſh, which is a mark of Antichriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I think I need not enlarge on this Point, for all that ſprinkle Children with Water, all that Preach Chriſt without, as he is in Heaven above at the Right Hand of God, all that Preach out of the Scripture, all that are Miniſters, and not Quakers, all that Pay Tithes, or receive Tithes, are of that abominable Tribe, for whom God's Dreadful Vengeance is reſerved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In fine, all, not Quakers, are Falſe Miniſters, by the Doctrine of the Quakers. And now it remains to ſhew what the Quakers call them in their Book, <hi>A Brief Diſcovery of a Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Eſtate of Antichriſt,</hi> &amp;c. under the Tithes, as in <hi>p.</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Falſe Miniſtry.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>The Prieſts of the World are, I. Conjurers, raiſing dead Doctrine, dead Uſes, dead Motives, dead Reaſons out of the Letter, which is Death; raiſing Death out of Death, notable Conjurers. II. Thieves and Robbers. III. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> cannot ſhew any Scripture for their <hi>Heatheniſh ways,</hi> and Beſtial Worſhips. IV. Witches, blind Guides. V. Devils, the Serpent is Head in them. VI. Lyars, the Commiſſion and Call of <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, <hi>Come from</hi> Oxford <hi>and</hi> Cambridge, <hi>which they call the Well-head of Divinity; corrupt Streams iſſue from thence I can witneſs [fetching the ſame Commodities] drinking a Cup of the ſame Poyſonous Fountain; the Fountain is bitter, the Streams are no better.</hi> Even the Sir <hi>Symons</hi> of the Age run to <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge:</hi> Theſe are not Miniſters of Chriſt, but Stewards of the Devil's Magazine, Diſſemblers and Lyars. VII. A Viperous and Serpentine Generation, going about to Murder and Strangle the Child Jeſus, holding a Worm-eaten, Beaſtly Form. VIII. Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, yea, of the Devil, fearful Blaſphemers. IX. Scarlet-coloured Beaſts: A Harlot full of Abominations and Filthineſs. X <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Merchants, Selling Beaſtly Wares for a large Price; <hi>the Letter,</hi> which is Duſt and Death: The day is coming when theſe Idol Merchants, theſe coſtly Sermon-makers, ſhall cry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> XI. Whited Walls, profeſſing nothing but Poyſonous ſtuff. XII. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Wolves. XIII. Greedy Dogs, really they are Blood-Hounds, ſtill hunting
<pb facs="tcp:65698:6"/>
and gaſping after their Prey, like the mouth of Hell; barking and raging like <hi>Sodomites.</hi> XIV. <hi>Eminent and Ambitious Phariſees</hi> of the Devil; woe, woe, woe, was the Portion of theſe Phariſees then, and woe, woe, woe, is their Portion now: And woe and miſery is the Portion of the upholders <hi>(whether King or Parliament)</hi> of that Treacherous and Deceitful Generation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Come, <hi>G. W.</hi> you ſay, <hi>Soft a little, we Charitably diſtinguiſh,</hi> &amp;c. But now your Spirit, your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Practice by your Books, are found out; and the Reaſon why you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to meet me, according to your Propoſal, is now found out; for you know you muſt either Juſtifie theſe your Antichriſtian and abominable Books, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them; Condemn them you will not, for that they are given forth by your great Apoſtle <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Diſciples, and (as you ſay) by the Eternal, Infallible Spirit of God, for then down goes your Infallibility, and great will be the fall thereof. Juſtifie them, you cannot; for if you tell them theſe ſayings came from Heaven, they'll tell you they came from Hell; ſo that here is a Gulf between you and them: You may fret and fume, rage and rail, invert, pervert, gloſs, and paint, but all to no purpoſe; I have hem'd you up, and caſt a Trench about you, and taken you as in a Net, and reſolve to hold you faſt; for I will not leave the deciſion of our Controverſie to Quakers, Ranters, <hi>Muggletonians,</hi> nor to your Grandſire the Pope. Come, <hi>G. W.</hi> I have not done with you yet; you ſay, <hi>The Quak. Vind. p.</hi> 2. <hi>As for Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, Scripturally conſidered, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and own,</hi> &amp;c. But, may ſome ſay, how is this poſſible, who have not baptized any with Water, nor received the Sacrament, under the Elements of Bread and Wine, theſe 40 years? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let me Interpret their meaning, which I take to be thus: They own them Scripturally, that is, as they own the Scriptures, they own the Sacraments; alſo upon the ſame Hypotheſis, they may ſay, they own the Scriptures Sacramentally, <hi>viz.</hi> as they own the Sacraments of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, when alas, they own neither, no otherwiſe than <hi>Arius</hi> owned the Faith of one Subſtance; who, when at the demand of the Emperour, he ſigned the <hi>Nicene Creed,</hi> who before-hand wrote his own Opinion in a piece of Paper, and put it in his Boſom under his Coat; and coming to the Book, he takes his Oath, that he verily believed as he had written, meaning as he had written in the Paper under his Coat. In like manner the Quakers confeſs and own the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord's Supper Scripturally; that is, as they have written in their own Books. And I pray, may ſome ſay, how is that? For Anſwer, you may ſee the ſame Juggle, read <hi>News coming up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>So duſt is the Serpent's meat, their Original is but duſt, which is but the Letter, which is Death; and their Goſpel is duſt,</hi> Matthew, Mark, Luke, <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>which is the Letter.</hi> Thus then they own the Scriptures Sacramentally, <hi>viz. to be Duſt, Death, and Serpents meat.</hi> And I will ſhew you how they own and confeſs the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, <hi>viz.</hi> as they own the Scriptures; for Proof thereof, ſee a Book of their own writing (only they are not ſo cunning as <hi>Arius,</hi> for he never Printed his Paper,) I ſay, ſee <hi>News coming up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>A <hi>Voice</hi> to all you deceivers, who deceive the People; and Blaſphemers, who utter forth your Blaſphemies and Hypocriſies, that tell People of a Sacrament, and tell them it is the Ordinance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> God. Bluſh, Bluſh and Tremble you who live in the Witchery, and bewitch the People <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                  </hi> Thus Reader,
<pb facs="tcp:65698:7"/>
I have ſhewed how they own the Lord's Supper Scripturally, and the Scripture Sacramentally; which though they have Printed the ſame, yet they are as loath to ſhew their Books of this kind to Authority, as <hi>Arius</hi> was his Paper, yet <hi>Arius</hi> could never pretend fairer to the Emperour, than <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> in the <hi>Quak. Vind. &amp;c.</hi> did to the Parliament: The like might be ſaid about their owning the Faſt commanded by Authority, <hi>p.</hi> 3. of their Vind. <hi>For the Intent, Subſtance, and End of a true Faſt, this we are frequently mindful of, &amp;c.</hi> Oh deceit! when 'tis gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally known through the Nation, that on the days ſet apart by Authority for a Faſt, they follow their outward Callings, open their Shops, and not ſo much as appoint a Meeting for that end, as others have done. I have not room to ſhew the depth of Hypocriſie in this <hi>Whitehead;</hi> 'tis like his Pretence (of late Years) of owning the Scriptures, and preferring them before all the Books in the World, but he means Sacramentally. If he deny my Interpretation of their Reſerves, then let him ſhew me that any one Quaker in <hi>England</hi> of the <hi>Foxonian Tribe,</hi> in Print hath recommended the Reading of the Scripture in their Religious Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings [if ſuch I may call them,] As they frequently do their own Epiſtles; for inſtance, ſee <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtle for the Remnant of Friends,</hi> &amp;c. where he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes thus: <hi>Let this</hi> [Epiſtle] <hi>be Read <hi>diſtinctly</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Here muſt not be a Syllable miſtaken, for it came from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Quakers: And yet I queſtion it, for in <hi>pag.</hi> 12. he compares the Sufferings of the Quakers to the Sufferings of Chriſt, like his Brother <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs. E. B</hi>'s. Works.</note> 
                  <hi>in the Life and Authority of God, from whence it came, amongst Friends in and about</hi> London, <hi>and elſewhere, as Friends are moved in the ſame Life, &amp;c.</hi> To this Inſtance let me add <hi>Whitehead</hi>'s Doctrine, in his Book, <hi>A Serious Apology,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>That what is ſpoken by the Spirit of Truth in any</hi> (meaning the Quakers) <hi>is of as great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as the Scriptures and Chapters are, and <hi>greater.</hi>
                  </hi> And for further Proof that they value their own Pamphlets above the Scripture, ſee <hi>New Rome Arraigned,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Introd.</hi> 10 <hi>Inſtances,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 40. to 47. And <hi>Quakeriſm withering,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 32. to 44. By which I have proved both from Matter of Fact and Practice, what I charge them with, beyond all their gloſſing.</p>
               <p>And now I am leaving <hi>G. W.</hi> I apply my ſelf to the Hearers amongſt the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and do Solemnly profeſs, that I never wrote one Book out of Malice, as he ſuggeſts; and as may appear in every Book, by the Propoſals and Offers I therein make. But if you do not call out <hi>G. W.</hi> and cauſe him to ſtand to his Propoſal, or elſe condemn and cenſure his Errors, and the Errors in your Friends Books, by him vindicated, under 12, or more of your hands, I do purpoſe, if the Lord per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, to proceed to a Brief Hiſtory of the Riſe, Growth, and Progreſs of Quaker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, from the Year 1650. to 1695. And the Projects of <hi>G. Fox,</hi> the Founder of Quakeriſm. And <hi>wherein their Principles are Antichriſtian, Antimagiſtratical, Irrational, Unreaſonable,</hi> Tending to ſubvert the Chriſtian Faith, to introduce <hi>Mahumetiſm,</hi> Atheiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to ſhew that their Faith and Doctrine is contrary to that of the Primitive Chriſtians, Saints, and Martyrs in all Ages. Firſt, in denying Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> contemning the Scriptures, reviling the Magiſtrates, reproaching the Miniſters of the Goſpel, undervaluing the Death and Sufferings of Chriſt, and exalting their own [of which many are meer Cheats, particularly <hi>Sam. Cater</hi>'s<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> New Rome un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                        <desc>••••…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>57.</hi>
                  </note>, who is recorded to have
<pb facs="tcp:65698:7"/>
ſuffered 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> where he never loſt a groat, but had 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> ſent him from <hi>London;</hi> ſo that inſtead of loſing 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> for Preaching, he got 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> clear; and many other things which may occur, which may be prevented by a ſincere Retractation. And let not <hi>G. W</hi>'s. Cunning, and ſmooth, and demure Carriage prevent you from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning what is Erroneous; for though he ſtudy no Events, nor fear no Effects, as he ſays, yet I would have you be wiſer. For whatever you think (as ſome of his Friends have told him in <hi>Barkſhire</hi> to his Face) 'tis he that hath been the chief diſturber; 'tis he that hath poyſoned the minds of many well-meaning People, 'tis his falſe gloſſing, and baſe perverting, that hath drawn the edge of my Pen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you; and if you will ſtand by him, and not, like the Wiſe Woman of <hi>Abel,</hi> bring him forth, nor condemn his Errors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> my Hand will be ſtill heavier upon you, if God permit me length of days, and the aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit. For I do tell you, his Impudence hath exceeded all that ever I read of, none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in perverting and falſe gloſſing. And if this Anſwer had not come out, I was minded by a quarter of a Sheet to give you a ſecond Summons, whether you hear or forbear. For I find <hi>G. W.</hi> will not come forth himſelf, he feareth the Fate of <hi>Hungate</hi> the Jeſuit againſt <hi>Hall.</hi> See <hi>New Rome unmask'd,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 33. to 49. Oh Friends! for ſo I can call many of you, I am grieved to ſee you willingly ignorant; and as I have already, ſo I could ſtill take great pains to inform you of the ſubtil working of ſome of your Juggling Teachers, whoſe Books are of two ſorts, and carry two faces, as I have often ſaid; ſaying one while, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are Death, Duſt, Serpents Meat, Beaſtly Ware, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, ſo uncertain, that whether <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Hermes</hi> be the firſt Penman is doubtful: But your <hi>Bellarmine G.W.</hi> to ſerve a turn, told the Parliament in your <hi>Vind. &amp;c.</hi> that the Quakers believed it to be given by Divine Inſpiration. Now, Friends, one of theſe Books, which teach thus contrary to each other, muſt be wrong; then let it be condemned. Again, <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, you prefer the Scriptures before all Books extant; and yet he himſelf teach by his <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> p. 49. <hi>That what is ſpoken from the Spirit of Truth in any, is of as great Authority as the Scriptures and Chapters are, and <hi>greater,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> And now you ſhall ſee how by Practice he prefers his own Writings before the Scripture, for he never recommended a Chapter of the Bible to be read in their Meetings of Worſhip: But you ſhall ſee how he impoſeth the Reading his own, and you, poor hearts, are obliged to hear it read, <hi>viz. An Epiſtle for the Remnant of Friends,</hi> by <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> which concludes thus: <hi>Let this</hi> [Epiſtle] <hi>be read di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly in the Life and Authority of God, from whence it came, amongst Friends in and about</hi> London, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now I appeal to your Conſciences, which does <hi>G. W.</hi> prefer think-ye? Again, <hi>G. Fox,</hi> in Anſwer to <hi>C. W. Great Myſt.</hi> p. 246. ſaid, <hi>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are <hi>not</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of God, as thou Blaſphemouſly affirmed;</hi> when upon his own Epiſtle he ſet this <hi>Encomium, This <hi>is</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of the Lord God to you, all.</hi> Again, <hi>Several Papers given forth by G. Fox,</hi> he there tells his Friends, <hi>This is the Word of the Lord: I charge you in the Preſence of the Living God, to ſend this</hi> [Epiſtle] <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst all Friends and Brethren every where, to be read in all Metetings: To them all this is <hi>the Word of God,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. Oh Friends! when did ever <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſay ſo of the Scriptures? No, he is ſo far from that, that he ſays, <hi>'Tis Blaſphemy to call the Scriptures the Word of God.</hi> Pray mark the irreconcileable Difference, and yet
<pb facs="tcp:65698:8"/>
your <hi>Bellarmine, G. W.</hi> had the Face to tell the Parliament they prefer the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before all Books in the World. Oh horrible Impudence! Again, ſee your Book, <hi>Truth</hi>'s <hi>Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 2. 104. where they Teach, you may as well burn the Scriptures as their Writings; and their Convocation, or <hi>London</hi> Yearly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, 1675. confirm them by Decree, ſaying, <hi>It is our Judgment in the Fear of God, and Authority of his Power, that no ſuch ſlight Names,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicts <hi>or</hi> Cannons, <hi>be put upon Friends Papers, which we Teſtifie have been given forth by the Spirit of God,</hi> &amp;c. Now, when did they ever ſend out a Decree, that no ſuch ſlight Names and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as Duſt, Death, Serpents Meat, Beaſtly Ware, Carnal Letter, Husk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be caſt upon the Scriptures? No, no, they were ſo far from that, that the very Men that gave the Scriptures theſe contemptuous Names, ſent out this Preſervative for their own Books, Papers, and Queries. Oh, Friends! what do you think of <hi>G. W.</hi> Is he not made up of Impudence? The Difference is ſo great between the value they put upon their own Books, and that upon the Scriptures, that it can never be reconciled, nor Satisfaction made to them that tender the Glory of God, and the good of Souls with grateful Hearts for his Goodneſs in continuing the Bible to us through all Ages, but by Condemning the one ſort of the Quakers Books to the Fire, as <hi>Oxford</hi> lately did a Book of the ſame Nature. Why then will you not bring forth <hi>Sheba, the Son of</hi> Bichri, <hi>that Man of Belial? G.W.</hi> Is there not a Wiſe Man amongſt you? He tells you that I wrong the Quakers in Charge, Citation, and Obſervation. Bring him forth according to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, and you will ſee it proved that I have not. I have given you a few In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, I might produce a hundred more, but time would fail. <hi>G. W.</hi> hath wrote to divers Clergy-Men to prevail with me to deſiſt; they give me his Letters, and wiſh me good Succeſs. Two of your Teachers have been with me within theſe two Months paſt, and uſed many Arguments with me; I tell them all is in vain, unleſs they bring forth <hi>Sheba.</hi> And ſo I ſay ſtill, or elſe come forth your ſelves, and condemn what is Erroneous, and defend what is Sound and Orthodox. And ſo I conclude, and ſubſcribe my ſelf your Friend in what I am able to do,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Milden-Hall,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 20. 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> Senior.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>John Gwillam,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopsgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65698:8"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
